Guide to the Jewish Labor Committee Northeast Region Records WAG.159
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jewish Labor Committee Northeast Region Records
1963-2002
1986-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.). Northeast Region.
Brown, Herman
WAG.159
8 Linear Feet in 19 manuscript boxes
The Jewish Labor Committee (JLC) was founded in 1934 by Jewish labor union leaders along with Jewish cultural associations to act in response to the rise of the Nazi Party in Europe. Before and during World War II, the JLC raised funds and organized people to fight the spread of the Nazi Party. Since the 1950s the JLC has worked to facilitate cooperation and communication between the Jewish community and labor, focusing on fighting prejudice and discrimination in the workforce. The Jewish Labor Committee Northeast Region Records document the work of the JLC office based in Boston, Massachusetts. The collection consists of subject files compiled by Herman Brown, the regional director of the JLC's Northeast Region, and dates between 1963 and 2002, with the bulk of the material dating between 1986 and 1998. These files contain correspondence, clippings, reports, and publications regarding the work of the JLC in New England.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Herman Brown, 1996. The accession number associated with this gift is 1984.017.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by folder title. The inventory lists box and folder numbers for an alphabetical range of titles. Folder titles that consist of a large amount of material are listed individually.
Historical Note
The Jewish Labor Committee (JLC) was founded in 1934 by Jewish labor union leaders with Jewish cultural associations to act in response to the rise of the Nazi Party in Europe. Before and during World War II, the JLC raised funds and organized people to fight the spread of the Nazi Party. Since the 1950s the JLC has worked to facilitate cooperation and communication between the Jewish community and labor, focusing on fighting prejudice and discrimination in the workforce. The Jewish Labor Committee Northeast Region is headquartered in Boston, Massachusetts and works with labor unions and organizations, religious organizations, and cultural organizations throughout New England.
Related Materials
The following Jewish Labor Committee materials are located at this repository:
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Records, Parts I (WAG 025.001), II (WAG 025.002), and III (WAG 025.003) Jewish Labor Committee, Chicago Records and Photographs (WAG 160)
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Oral History Collection (OH 027)
Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.) Photograph Collection (PHOTOS 048)
Jewish Labor Committee Ephemera (EPHEMERA ARTIFACTS 003)
Issues of JLC Review (HD8055.J4 A1), JLC Outlook (HD8055.J4 A17), and JLC Civil Rights Newsletter (JC585 .J533).
Scope and Contents
The Jewish Labor Committee Northeast Region Records document the work of the Jewish Labor Committee in New England, and dates between 1963 and 2002, with the bulk of the material dating between 1986 and 1998. The collection consists of subject files compiled by Herman Brown, the regional director of the Jewish Labor Committee's (JLC) Northeast Region. The files document the work of the JLC in New England, mainly in Massachusetts, through correspondence, clippings, reports, and publications. The correspondence documents the JLC's work with labor organizations, religious groups, cultural organizations, and government agencies to provide training, lobby for and against legislation, and organize events amongst these groups. The clippings and publications reflect the interests and work of the JLC and its partners. The reports document JLC meetings and programs, as well as conferences, trainings, and events sponsored by other groups.
Labor movement -- Religious aspects.; Labor unions and education -- United States.; Labor movement -- United States -- 20th century.; Interdenominational cooperation.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Newsletters.; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.); Brown, Herman
- Alman - Conference on Judaism in Rural New England and Southern Quebec, 1982-1998 (Box 1, Folder 1-18)
- Conference on Stress and Heart Attacks in the Workplace - Contributions and coalitions, 1986-1998 (Box 2, Folder 1-9)
- Correspondence, 1986-1998 (Box 2, Folder 10-13, Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Diamond Walnut strike - Federations and community relations councils, 1985-1997 (Box 3, Folder 3-16)
- Foreign labor rights - Forum on neo-Nazism in Germany, 1992-1997 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- Fundraising, 1976-1998 (Box 4, Folder 3-9)
- German educators - Harvard Union of Clerical and Technical Workers, 1987-1998 (Box 4, Folder 10-14)
- Health and safety, 1985-1998 (Box 4, Folder 15, Box 5, Folder 1-5)
- Health and Safety Committee - Healthcare, 1985-1992 (Box 5, Folder 6-12)
- Holocaust education, 1985-1998 (Box 5, Folder 13, Box 6, Folder 1-4)
- Housing - Industrial homework, 1986-1996 (Box 6, Folder 5-12)
- Israel, 1984-1998 (Box 6, Folder 13-14, Box 7, Folder 1-14, Box 8, Folder 1-7)
- Issues - Jerusalem 3000, 1986-1998 (Box 8, Folder 8-11)
- Jewish Community Relations Council of Greater Boston, 1988-1998 (Box 8, Folder 12-14, Box 9, Folder 1-4)
- Jewish Labor Committee, 1963-2002 (Box 9, Folder 5-13, Box 10, Folder 1-3)
- Jewish Vocational Service - Labor Guild, 1986-1997 (Box 10, Folder 4-14)
- Labor history, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Labor solidarity, 1988-1994 (Box 11, Folder 2-9)
- Labor support, 1995-1998 (Box 11, Folder 10-12, Box 12, Folder 1)
- Leadership Network - Legal, 1985-1987 (Box 12, Folder 2-5)
- Legislation, 1985-1998 (Box 12, Folder 6-13)
- Libraries - Maine, 1986-1995 (Box 12, Folder 14, Box 13, Folder 1)
- Massachusetts AFL-CIO, 1985-1998 (Box 13, Folder 2-8)
- Massachusetts Coalition for Adult Literacy - Massachusetts Health Action Alliance, 1983-1989 (Box 13, Folder 9-12)
- Massachusetts Interfaith Committee for Worker Justice, 1996-1998 (Box 13, Folder 13-16)
- Massachusetts Labor Committee on the Middle East - Miscellaneous, 1984-1998 (Box 14, Folder 1-12)
- National Health Insurance, 1989-1990 (Box 14, Folder 13-14, Box 15, Folder 1-2)
- National Yiddish Book Center - Prevailing wage, 1985-1998 (Box 15, Folder 3-12)
- Programs, 1986-1995 (Box 16, Folder 1-5)
- Public Affairs Committee - Publicity, 1979-1995 (Box 16, Folder 6-10)
- Religion and labor, 1991-1997 (Box 16, Folder 11-14, Box 17, Folder 1-2)
- Reports, 1986-1998 (Box 17, Folder 3-7)
- Rhode Island - Southeastern Massachusetts, 1986-1998 (Box 17, Folder 8-14)
- Soviet Jewry, 1985-1990 (Box 17, Folder 15, Box 18, Folder 1-2)
- The Tax Equity Alliance for Massachusetts - Women's issues, 1985-1998 (Box 18, Folder 3-16)
- Work Environment Justice Fund, 1994-1996 (Box 19, Folder 1-6)
- Workers' compensation - The Workmen's Circle, 1985-1987 (Box 19, Folder 7-8)